<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article doi="28" language="cs" publication_type="full_text"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <titles>
    <title>Responzivní design a automatická sazba s Lua<LaTeX/>em</title>
  </titles>
  <contributors>
    <person_name contributor_role="author" sequence="first">
      <given_name>Michal</given_name>
      <surname>Hoftich</surname>
    </person_name>
  </contributors>
  <pages>
    <first_page>28</first_page>
    <last_page>38</last_page>
  </pages>
  <additional-content>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Tento článek představuje využití metod responzivního designu
        a pokročilých vlastností Lua<LaTeX/>u pro automatickou sazbu dokumentů
        určených pro různé cílové výstupy, jak tištěné, tak elektronické,
        například mobilní telefony, tablety nebo čtečky e-knih.
      </para>
      <para>
        Konkrétně se zaměřuje na využití Lua<LaTeX/>u pro automatizovanou sazbu
        s pomocí balíčků Responsive pro nastavení velikosti písma a řádkování
        podle velikosti stránky, Luavlna pro zamezení výskytu jednopísmenných
        předložek na koncích řádků, Lua-widow-control pro omezení osamocených
        řádků na koncích a začátcích stránek a Linebreaker, který brání
        přetečení řádků.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <title>Responsive Design and Automatic Typesetting with Lua<LaTeX/></title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This article focuses on the use of responsive design techniques to
        display web pages on devices with different display sizes, such as
        mobile phones, tablets, large monitors and printers. These methods
        allow optimizing the readability of a document on all devices by using
        different font sizes, individual page elements, and margins.
      </para>
      <para>
        We present how similar functionality can be achieved using <LaTeX/>.
        Specifically, it focuses on the use of Lua<LaTeX/> for automated
        typesetting, using packages Responsive for setting font size and line
        spacing according to page size, Luavlna to prevent the occurrence of
        single-letter prepositions at line breaks, Lua-widow-control to reduce
        orphan lines at page breaks and page starts, and Linebreaker to prevent
        line overflow.
      </para>
      <para>
        With these methods, a single source document can be used for different
        outputs, such as print versions, e-book readers, and web pages, and
        achieve optimal document display on all devices.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </additional-content>
  <!-- <xi:include href="citations.Hoftich-responsive.xml"/> -->
</article>
